export const HISTORYA2016 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. The study of history makes one to be",
A: "Law abiding",
B: "Hard Working",
C: "Tolerant of people’s ideas and cultures",
D: "knowledgeable about the economies of countries",
answer: "C. Tolerant of people’s ideas and cultures",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. Archaeological information is reliable because it is",
A: "Mostly kept in good and reliable museums",
B: "Obtained from artifacts which could be seen and touched",
C: "Derived from learned people",
D: "Free from bias and exaggeration",
answer: "B. Obtained from artifacts which could be seen and touched",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. Public opinion concerning a historical event is a part of",
A: "oral tradition",
B: "carbon dating",
C: "linguistic evidence",
D: "archaeological evidence",
answer: "A. oral tradition",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The interdisciplinary approach is recommended for the writing of African history because",
A: "the information cannot be easily obtained and learnt",
B: "it enables a historian to recall the past",
C: "it puts together information from the relevant fields of knowledge",
D: "to put more emphasis on the political aspects of the people",
answer: "C. it puts together information from the relevant fields of knowledge",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. Which of following statement best describes the problem of oral tradition? It",
A: "Involves travelling from place to place to gather information",
B: "Makes history lesson very difficult for students",
C: "Makes people accept the authenticity of the information",
D: "Is easy for people to exaggerate and distort its information",
answer: "D. Is easy for people to exaggerate and distort its information",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. The ethnic group noted for harassment of the caravan traders were the",
A: "Berber",
B: "Arab",
C: "Tureg",
D: "Hausa",
answer: "C. Tureg",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. Camel used in the trans-Saharan trade was nicknamed ‘ship of the desert’ because",
A: "Its body looked like a ship on the sea",
B: "It could carry many goods on its back",
C: "It was used by coastal traders in carrying goods",
D: "It was a description given by the Romans",
answer: "B. It could carry many goods on its back",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. Hausa land became famous during the caravan trade due to",
A: "Its exports of hides and skins",
B: "Many magnificent mosques it possessed",
C: "Its great import of honey and gum",
D: "The abundance of gold in the area",
answer: "A. Its exports of hides and skins",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. The trans-Saharan trade started to decline from the sixteenth century mainly due to the",
A: "shortage of gold and ivory in western Sudan",
B: "increase in inter-ethnic wars in western Sudanese state",
C: "Failure of the rulers of western Sudanese states to protect the traders",
D: "increase in the economic activities of European traders along the coast",
answer: "D. increase in the economic activities of European traders along the coast",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. The spread of Islam into the forest areas of West Africa was mostly done by the",
A: "Berber",
B: "Hausa",
C: "Mande Dyula",
D: "Tuareg",
answer: "C. Mande Dyula",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. The introduction and spread of Islam in West Africa led to the",
A: "Decline of Christianity",
B: "Increase in agricultural production",
C: "Dethronement of many chiefs",
D: "Promotion of indigenous administration",
answer: "D. Promotion of indigenous administration",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. Islamic scholars in Western Sudanese were important because they",
A: "Determined the items of trade",
B: "Kept historical records of the states",
C: "Collected taxes on the caravan routes",
D: "Helped in setting up markets",
answer: "B. Kept historical records of the states",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. One of the reasons for coming of Europeans to West Africa was",
A: "The desire for wealth and fame",
B: "To establish economic stability",
C: "To learn West African languages",
D: "To enhance West African settlements",
answer: "A. The desire for wealth and fame",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. The early European settlements along the coast of West Africa made the areas",
A: "Inaccessible to Africans",
B: "Develop into strategies points",
C: "Economically unstable",
D: "Havens of criminals",
answer: "B. Develop into strategies points",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. A significant development along the coast of West Africa as a result of the European presence was the",
A: "Rise and development of towns",
B: "Dethronement of all traditional chiefs",
C: "Conversion of all traditional rulers to Christianity",
D: "Promotion of West African cultures",
answer: "A. Rise and development of towns",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. Europeans trades refused to sell firearms to West Africans at initial stage because",
A: "Their governments forbade them",
B: "Firearms would reduce inter-ethnic wars",
C: "The Europeans did not have enough to sell",
D: "They could be used against them",
answer: "D. They could be used against them",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. European traders in West Africa in the seventeenth century changed from trading in gold arid ivory to, slaves due to the",
A: "Discovery of America by Christopher Columbus",
B: "shortage of labour on American plantations",
C: "increase demand for slaves by Christian missionaries",
D: "Industrial Revolution in Europe",
answer: "A. The Discovery of America by Christopher Columbus",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. The trans-Atlantic slave trade involved the participation of",
A: "Asia, Europe and Africa",
B: "Europe, Asia and the Americas",
C: "Europe, Africa and the Americas",
D: "The Americas, Africa and Asia",
answer: "C. Europe, Africa and the Americas",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. The Dominicans friar, Las Casas, recommended the use of African slaves on the American plantations because the Africans",
A: "were less hostile",
B: "were devout Christians",
C: "were willing to work there",
D: "could withstand the weather",
answer: "D. could withstand the weather (This is a common but inaccurate justification for the use of African slaves.)",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. One of the efforts made by Britain to end the trans-Atlantic slave trade was the",
A: "huge compensation paid to African rulers",
B: "military confrontation against some European nations",
C: "establishment of naval squadrons on west African coast",
D: "inauguration of the Berlin West Africa Conference",
answer: "C. establishment of naval squadrons on west African coast",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. The suppression of the trans-Atlantic slave trade took a long time because",
A: "the economic and political organizations of Africans were based on trade",
B: "Africans and Europeans were busy expanding their territories",
C: "the suffering of the slaves was yet to be known to the world",
D: "the slaves themselves were not interested in their freedom",
answer: "A. the economic and political organizations of Africans were based on trade",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. The most important factor which led to the abolition of the slave trade was the",
A: "Industrial Revolution",
B: "drought in the West Indies",
C: "lack of suitable ship",
D: "decline in the supply of slaves",
answer: "A. The Industrial Revolution",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. The emergence of educated elite during the era of Christian missionary activities led to the",
A: "gradual emergence of nationalist movement in West Africa",
B: "mass movement of the educated elite to Europe",
C: "total breakdown of traditional institution in West Africa",
D: "increase in the efforts to dethrone traditional rules",
answer: "A. gradual emergence of nationalist movement in West Africa",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. The Christian missions in West Africa were involved in the following activities except",
A: "propagation of Christianity",
B: "promotion of Western education",
C: "building of forts and castles",
D: "introduction of cash drop",
answer: "C. building of forts and castles",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. The major problem which hindered the activities of the Christian mission in West Africa in the 19th century was",
A: "trans-Atlantic slave trade",
B: "language barrier",
C: "the activities of educated elite",
D: "insufficient food",
answer: "B. language barrier",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. A major impact of Christian missionary activities on West Africa was the",
A: "deforestation of fertile land",
B: "introduction of Western civilization",
C: "abolition of traditional customs and practices",
D: "training of catechists",
answer: "B. introduction of Western civilization",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. Christian missionaries introduced new farming and commercial methods to the people West Africa in order to",
A: "make them import raw materials from Europe",
B: "improve their standard of living",
C: "limit missionary activities",
D: "employ more farmers from Europe",
answer: "B. improve their standard of living",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. An important method of territory acquisition in West Africa by the Europeans in the 19th century was the",
A: "enlightenment of West Africans",
B: "liberation of trade and commerce",
C: "supply of arms and ammunition to West African states",
D: "signing of treaties with the local chiefs",
answer: "D. signing of treaties with the local chiefs",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. The need for the supply pf resources and capital to Europe was the main reason for the",
A: "Christian missionary activities",
B: "introduction of Western education",
C: "granting of independence to West African states",
D: "colonial subjugation of West Africa",
answer: "D. colonial subjugation of West Africa",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. The French acquired most of West African territories by",
A: "purchase of land",
B: "the force of arms",
C: "bribing the local chiefs",
D: "persuading the local inhabitants",
answer: "B. the force of arms",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. Some people in the French West African colonies protested against the harshness of colonial rule in the 20th century",
A: "resorting to strike actions",
B: "embarking on hunger strikes",
C: "embarking on mass migration",
D: "resorting to insurgency",
answer: "A. resorting to strike actions",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. One of the effects of the Berlin Conference in West Africa was that it",
A: "did not allow Christian missionary activities",
B: "subjected European nations to harsh rule",
C: "gave rise to resistance movement by Africans",
D: "displeased European Heads of State",
answer: "C. gave rise to resistance movement by Africans",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. In order to avoid clash of interests on acquisition of territories in West Africa, the Europeans agreed at the Berlin Conference that",
A: "effective occupation should be r.1ade by any claiming power",
B: "military confrontation be made against disobedient African leaders",
C: "Economic sanction to be imposed on West African states",
D: "Ethnic groups must be divided into sub-groups",
answer: "A. effective occupation should be r.1ade by any claiming power",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. During the first phase of colonialism, all West African societies had the same objective of",
A: "Escaping to Europe",
B: "Adopting European culture",
C: "Submitting to colonial control",
D: "Defending their sovereignty",
answer: "D. Defending their sovereignty",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. The colonialists participated in succession disputes in West Africa by",
A: "By supporting one faction against the other",
B: "Taking their favourites to their Head of State",
C: "Supporting the building of empires",
D: "Boosting Christian missionary activities",
answer: "A. By supporting one faction against the other",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. Some West African leaders resorted to military approaches in dealing with colonialists whenever they",
A: "Were trusted by the Europeans",
B: "Betrayed the Europeans",
C: "Aligned with the Europeans",
D: "Were betrayed by the Europeans",
answer: "D. Were betrayed by the Europeans",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Reaction among Muslim states of West Africa to colonialism was heightened because they",
A: "Believed that Europeans were infidels",
B: "Needed modernization",
C: "Liked the Europeans’ approaches",
D: "Understood European languages very well",
answer: "A. Believed that Europeans were infidels",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. A feature of colonial economic policy in West Africa was",
A: "The development of industries",
B: "Economic diversification",
C: "Creation of wealthy economic class",
D: "Production of raw materials for export",
answer: "D. Production of raw materials for export",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. A remarkable influence of the Second World War on West Africa was on",
A: "Spiritual development",
B: "Nationalist struggles",
C: "Educational development",
D: "Communication enhancement",
answer: "B. Nationalist struggles",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. Which of the following best explains the problem of West African countries?",
A: "Leadership crisis·",
B: "Inadequate natural resources",
C: "Political contest",
D: "Multiple ethnic groups",
answer: "A. Leadership crisis·",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. Foreign aid to West African states after independence was criticized for promoting",
A: "Neo-colonialism in West Africa",
B: "Democracy in West Africa.",
C: "Independence of West Africa",
D: "Industrialization in West Africa",
answer: "A. Neo-colonialism in West Africa",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. One major evidence of neo-colonialism in West Africa was the",
A: "Adoption of the political system of ex-colonial powers",
B: "Spending of vacation in America by West Africans",
C: "Adoption of Western culture in West Africa",
D: "Adoption of Portuguese currencies by West African states",
answer: "A. Adoption of the political system of ex-colonial powers",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. Most West African countries achieved their independence through",
A: "Armed struggle",
B: "Bribery and kickbacks",
C: "Appeal to the British Queen",
D: "Constitutional reforms",
answer: "D. Constitutional reforms",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. All the following were the factors for military interventions in West African politics except",
A: "Over-ambition of some military leaders",
B: "High prices of some essential goods",
C: "Suppression of traditional religion",
D: "Corruption and nepotism",
answer: "C. Suppression of traditional religion",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Which of the following events was a source of boundary disputes in West Africa?",
A: "the Decolonization of West Africa",
B: "Independence of West African states",
C: "Beth Conference of is",
D: "Industrial Revolution",
answer: "A. The Decolonization of West Africa",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. One of the benefits which West African states derived from membership of the Economic Community of West African states was that",
A: "They regularly paid their dues",
B: "They enjoyed the use of common currency",
C: "Their leaders regularly exchanged ideas at meetings",
D: "They had a centralized administrative system",
answer: "C. They enjoyed the use of common currency",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. In what way did West African states play an effective role in achieving the objectives of the United Nations? They",
A: "Took part in the United Nations games",
B: "Trained all the United Nations experts in West Africa",
C: "Traded with other member states",
D: "Took part in peace-keeping operations",
answer: "D. Took part in peace-keeping operations",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. The United Nations Organization was important in the decolonization of West Africa because",
A: "Britain was one of the countries with veto power",
B: "It focused on the provision of health facilities",
C: "It encouraged other member countries to help the colonized people",
D: "One of its main objectives was the emancipation of the colonized people",
answer: "D. One of its main objectives was the emancipation of the colonized people",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. The Organization of African Unity (OAU) was classified as",
A: "An offshoot of the United Nation Organization (UNO)",
B: "A brain child of the Commonwealth of Nations",
C: "A regional peace keeping force",
D: "A league of sovereign African States",
answer: "D. A league of sovereign African States",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. 25th May 1963 was an important landmark in the history of Africa because it was the day when",
A: "South Africa gained her independence.",
B: "African leaders joined the Non-Aligned Movement",
C: "African leaders set up the African High Court",
D: "The Organization of African Unity’s charter was signed",
answer: "D. The Organization of African Unity’s charter was signed",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},


]